<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Not Your Average End User]]></title>
  <link href="http://klatz.co/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://klatz.co/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-03T20:50:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://klatz.co/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Klatzco]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Automatically Back Up Terraria Saves/Worlds With a Script]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/terraria-backup-script/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-03T19:18:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/terraria-backup-script</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently set up a Terraria server to play on with new friends from school. I wanted regular backups, so I cobbled together a quick backup script. Here&rsquo;s how to set it up.</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<p>Should work on Windows 7, may require fine-tuning on other versions.</p>

<p>First, download the <a href="1">command line version of 7zip</a>, and extract the contents of the zip file to C:\7zip (make the 7zip folder, it doesn&rsquo;t exist).</p>

<p>Put the following in a text file, and rename it &ldquo;terrariabackup.bat&rdquo; or whatever you&rsquo;d like. (You may need to enable viewing file extensions - google it). You can put the script wherever you&rsquo;d like, but I recommend &ldquo;C:\Users\USERNAME\Documents\My Games\Terraria\backup&rdquo; (make the backup folder), because you&rsquo;ll have to change the script if you want it elsewhere.</p>

<p>You MUST make the backup folder, or you can delete the second line of the script and your backups will start accumulating in the directory the script is in.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>&#8220;Terraria Backup Script&#8221;</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='batch'><span class='line'>C:\<span class="m">7</span>zip\<span class="m">7</span>za a -tzip <span class="nv">%date:~4</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="m">2</span>%-<span class="nv">%date:~7</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="m">2</span>%-<span class="nv">%date:~10</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="m">4</span><span class="nv">%_%</span>TIME:~<span class="m">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="m">2</span>%.<span class="nv">%TIME:~3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="m">2</span><span class="nv">%_</span>.zip <span class="s2">&quot;%USERPROFILE%\Documents\My Games\Terraria\Players&quot;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;%USERPROFILE%\Documents\My Games\Terraria\Worlds&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>move <span class="s2">&quot;%date:~4,2%-%date:~7,2%-%date:~10,4%_%TIME:~0,2%.%TIME:~3,2%_.zip&quot;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;%USERPROFILE%\Documents\My Games\Terraria\backup&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>%USERPROFILE% is just a shortcut for C:\Users\YOUR USERNAME.</p>

<p>You can click on the &ldquo;terrariabackup.bat&rdquo; script to test it. Don&rsquo;t forget the backup folder. If it works, you should see a file in the backup folder with the current date and time as the filename. If so, proceed to the next step. If not, fiddle around a bit or contact me.</p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ve got to make a backup task in Task Scheduler. Search for it in the start menu.</p>

<p>Click Action > Create Task. Name it &ldquo;Terraria Backup&rdquo; or the like.</p>

<p>Click Triggers > New. Set the task to the frequency that you would like - click &ldquo;Daily&rdquo; and then &ldquo;Repeat task every:&rdquo;. Hit OK.</p>

<p>Click Actions > New. Under &ldquo;Program/script&rdquo;, put the path to the script. If it&rsquo;s in your Terraria folder, this is &ldquo;C:\Users\USERNAME\Documents\My Games\Terraria\backup\terrariabackup.bat&rdquo; (with quotes). Next to &ldquo;Start in (optional)&rdquo;, type in the directory that the script is in - should be &ldquo;C:\Users\USERNAME\Documents\My Games\Terraria\backup&rdquo; if you&rsquo;ve been following along.</p>

<p>Hit okay. You&rsquo;ll need to type in your password.</p>

<p>To test:</p>

<p>Click on Task Scheduler Library in the left pane.</p>

<p>Right click on the task and click run.</p>

<p>And that should do it! Let me know if you have any problems.</p>

<p>Thanks to <a href="2">this reddit post</a> for helping me out with the script.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Floppera]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/floppera/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-27T04:28:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/floppera</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever wanted to hear floppy drives sing?</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/w6tuMn5sPyM" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>


<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/m5Ho_ik_ofc" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>


<p>I stole some floppy drives from old computers in the basement and started following Sammy1Am&rsquo;s tutorial. The system is basically an Arduino, 5v power supply for the Arduino/floppies, a Java program, some Arduino code, and as many floppies as you want. I&rsquo;m not going to go in to how you set everything up, as that&rsquo;s been done plenty of times already. It&rsquo;s certainly been a lot of fun to play various music files in floppified version, though!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/google-tour/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-07T16:02:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/google-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I led a group of students to a tour at Google&rsquo;s Chicago office after school one day.</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/vGcEzka.jpg" alt="Google! With your truly looking like a putz in the middle." /></p>

<p>My school had a special half-day for Ash Wednesday to focus on immigration as a social justice issue. After a very unconvincing George W. Bush roleplay on my part for Model UN&rsquo;s event, we grabbed lunch, boarded some buses, and made our way over to Google&rsquo;s Chicago office (which is currently located on Dearborn and Kinzie). I&rsquo;d wanted to check out the office since I was a freshman, so this was an immensely cool experience for me.</p>

<p>Organizing the tour was particularly fun. When at a rather large MIT meeting in Oak Park back in the fall, I talked to an alum who also happened to have worked at Google. I asked him if he could give me a tour, and he gave me the contact of someone he knew there who&rsquo;s particularly interested in teaching kids about computer science. I shot him an email, and he replied in January, inviting me and a group of 20-25 &ldquo;engineering-focused students&rdquo; to come check out the office for a tour, informational session, and panel.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, we weren&rsquo;t allowed to take photos, barring the one above, but we saw a lot of the classic Googley-themed open office space that you might expect. The office spanned some eight or so floors, and featured things like kitchens stocked with healthy food, miniature museums (even a piece of Fermilab&rsquo;s particle accelerator!), and a gym.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Je90beb.jpg" alt="Visitor Badge." /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not quite sure what that QR code is - there seemed to be a sort of visitor kiosk at the main reception desk on the bottom-most floor - but it returns a string - &ldquo;$80AE86311/&rdquo;. Scanning friends&#8217; badges revealed slightly different numbers, just sequential changes in the last two digits (not including the forward slash). I&rsquo;m curious as to if that number format is anything special - please let me know if you know anything!</p>

<p>One of the most interesting rooms (and where we spent most of our time) felt like a classroom - this was something our tour guide mentioned as deliberate, citing how Google&rsquo;s major focus is on learning. Coming out of four years of eight hours, five days a week classes admittedly renders me a bit hesitant when thinking about an environment like that&hellip; but learning about computers! All day! That sounds really quite wonderful.</p>

<p>Coming out of the tour, I can&rsquo;t say that my opinion of computer science has changed too much - I&rsquo;m still pretty resolutely committed to it - but I certainly do have a better appreciation for what Google does, which is sell ads. And sell ads well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi: NES-PC]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/raspberry-pi-nes-pc/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T16:25:48-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/raspberry-pi-nes-pc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To wrap up an old loose end with a friend, I finished building an NES-themed media center PC built around a Raspberry Pi.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We had originally started this project way before the Raspberry Pi was released, towards the end of 2011 or so. The initial plans were to throw a full-size motherboard and laptop CD drive into an NES case, along with a PicoPSU. Beyond cannibalizing the NES case, we never finished the original project, so over winter break we decided to throw a Raspberry Pi inside and finally wrap things up.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/rsbb2/embed"></iframe>


<p>The Raspberry Pi is mounted on some screws attached to the bottom of the case. The controller ports are USB-to-NES, ordered online. The power button was manually resoldered and attached to Raspberry Pi pins according to online pinouts and tested (rather timidly for fear of shorts) until it worked. Power currently retains its original function, mirroring what it did on the original NES. Reset, however, is not soldering to anything, but the LED still functions.</p>

<p>The Raspberry Pi is running <a href="http://blog.petrockblock.com/retropie/">RetroPie</a>, a Raspbian derivative used for running emulators in a pretty fashion.</p>

<p>It was a lot of fun to build everything! especially getting the controllers in place, because we had to ad-lib so much of it. That&rsquo;s what made it my favorite part to build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Randy Pausch: Final Lecture]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/randy-pausch-final-lecture/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T03:33:26-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/randy-pausch-final-lecture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps a few years late, but I just found this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo">positively gorgeous final lecture by Randy Pausch</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As a wannabe computer science major/virtual reality geek, I&rsquo;m really glad that I can directly relate to some of the work he did, and he&rsquo;s got so many absolutely wonderful points throughout the entire video.</p>

<p>Something cool: At one point, he references a Pirates of the Carribean attraction he worked on. I remember going to that attraction, and thinking it was the <strong>coolest</strong> thing. Funny, the little ways you bump into people.</p>

<p>One moment that really shines: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo&amp;t=61m40s">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo&amp;t=61m40s</a></p>

<p>Originally found via <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo">this Jeff Atwood post</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Deal With MIT Deferral]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/how-i-deal-with-mit-deferral/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-14T22:04:22-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/how-i-deal-with-mit-deferral</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Curtly, by breaking stuff.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My mom was in a car accident a while back - she came out unscathed, but her car didn&rsquo;t. My dad got me the results of fixing it up. This is probably my favorite way to spend my Saturdays.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/aYQD3/embed"></iframe>


<p>does markdown even support html? let&rsquo;s find out.</p>

<p>Edit: Evidently yes.</p>

<p>I love timelapse videos, and iOS has recently implemented an option for recording them!</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/OmtuhTslYnA" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bridge Competition]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/bridge-competition/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-09T20:05:51-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/bridge-competition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my school&rsquo;s yearly events is a bridge competition put on by the science department and sponsored by a relatively successful construction company full of alumni. It&rsquo;s been running some twenty-odd years, and my physics teacher dangled tasty extra credit in front of our class in exchange for a competent bridge.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So I partnered up and we built a bridge, and then another bridge because we had the spare parts and felt like it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/54oTmdE.jpg" alt="stalkerphoto" />
//stopmotion</p>

<p>As it turns out, we didn&rsquo;t RTFM well enough (have I mentioned that&rsquo;s <a href="http://i.imgur.com/kBxXdCL.jpg">what I have on my class ring</a>?) and neither of the bridge qualified as they were. Some quick on-site edits (while decked out in a suit no less, captured by a friend sneakily snapping pics of me) rendered at least one of the bridges qualified, and we ended up holding a decently-respectable four bricks before the bridge broke. Not quite as stellar as we&rsquo;d hoped, but certainly better than not being able to test the bridges at all.</p>

<p>Frankly, I&rsquo;m happy that we learned the lesson of READ THE FRAKKING INSTRUCTIONS in a relatively low-stakes, mostly for-fun scenario such as this one. Better now than in some more exciting competition later down the road.</p>

<p>At the same time — not reading the instructions? I&rsquo;m embarrased. Our bridge was certainly better than my attempts freshman and sophomore years (paltry three-hour attempts cobbbled togther the night before, as opposed to actual collaborative 6hr fun making them), but not reading the instructions seems like such a terrible mistake to make. Never again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eagle Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/eagle-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-04T13:39:38-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/eagle-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago, I finished my Eagle Project.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><strong><em>UPDATE: <a href="http://lincolnwood.chicagotribune.com/2014/12/16/lincolnwood-teen-makes-benches-chicagos-misericordia/">I was featured in the local newspaper</a> (!!!)</em></strong></h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/6JeReaa.jpg" alt="completed" /></p>

<p>It was a massive effort (much bigger than I anticipated) that ended up taking a cumulative 200 man-hours, 40 of my own.</p>

<p>The project was constructing from scratch three massive, handicap-accessible picnic tables for this really awesome place called Misericordia (my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Misericordia_Home">first-ever wikipedia page!</a>). It&rsquo;s a super-cool not-for-profit organization that does some really awesome things for a lot of people with disabilites.</p>

<p>We ran into many bumps on the way, like not having all the wood, bolts, or washers, or splitting wood, but we more or less mitigated every problem pretty quickly by sending my dad out to pick up whatever we were missing.</p>

<p>&ldquo;We&rdquo; being the horde of young scouts and adult leaders that came and helped out.</p>

<p>I learned quite a few things about working with a lot of people — chiefly, organizing people is REALLY HARD — and I&rsquo;m pretty happy with how everything turned out.</p>

<p>We installed the tables at Misericordia&rsquo;s main campus, where they will sit unused until the spring comes. But before then, I&rsquo;ve gotta finish my Eagle Book, the binder reporting on the entire project.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been a ton of work, but I&rsquo;m happy that it&rsquo;s nearly done, and I&rsquo;m really hopeful that the tables will see some use and appreciation in the years to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T01:06:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here we are again&hellip;</p>

<p>I have, after some deliberation and much struggling with the command line, finally setup my blog once again! I will attempt to populate it with old posts and old timestamps, and will likely change the theme to something I like better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Github Pull Request: Woohoo!]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/first-github-pull-request-woohoo/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T11:40:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/first-github-pull-request-woohoo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I made my first Github pull request today, <a href="https://github.com/jdavis/twofactorauth/pull/161">visible here</a>. I learned some about how to pull. Though I figure it&rsquo;s time to learn Git bash rather than relying on the rather slow (but pretty!) GUI application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doge Shell Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/doge-shell-program/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T21:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/doge-shell-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend of mine showed me <a href="https://github.com/thiderman/doge">this absolute beauty</a>:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="https://github-camo.global.ssl.fastly.net/aec4c3fc2d674f2a4e90ed9e1413d95f204d7445/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f48784839716b612e706e67" alt="doge" /></p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t yet worked out how to get it running in Windows, though. Part of it must be the fact that cmd&rsquo;s a joke out of yesteryear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mysterious Mic Grate on Apple Earbuds]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/mysterious-mic-grate-on-apple-earbuds/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T19:48:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/mysterious-mic-grate-on-apple-earbuds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever noticed that Apple&rsquo;s signature earbuds have integrated microphones? There&rsquo;s a small grate of sorts on the back of the volume control switch attached to the standard TRRS earbuds (those with an extra ring on the jack) which seems to signify that there&rsquo;s some sort of mic contained within.</p>

<p>I happened to have a pair of well-loved, fairly beaten-up earbuds that have a crack in the middle of the switch. Naturally, they had to be dismantled. But what I found inside was a bit surprising.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/YOVNGnk.jpg" alt="Pic of crack" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/aZZIayA.jpg" alt="other side" /></p>

<p>It seems as if the microphone grate&hellip; doesn&rsquo;t actually lead anywhere. I guess the mic is still there, underneath the plastic, but that it doesn&rsquo;t actually need any holes to let sound in. That&rsquo;s pretty Apple.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playing With the Experiment on Google IO's Site]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/playing-with-the-experiment-on-google-ios-site/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T23:20:09-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/playing-with-the-experiment-on-google-ios-site</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking at <a href="https://developers.google.com/events/io">Google IO&rsquo;s website</a> (mostly with info for last year, so this is admittedly dated) I noticed an easter egg of sorts, a pretty Javascript application mysteriously titled <a href="https://developers.google.com/events/io/experiment">&ldquo;/experiment&rdquo;</a>. The first thing you notice is the fact you can click on the I&rsquo;s and the O&rsquo;s. The next is that your inputs are tracked on the bottom of the screen. And then you noticed that there are right inputs and wrong inputs.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/SoDk97S.png" alt="io experiment" /></p>

<p>So naturally I play around a bit, finding two combinations: 01010011, which yields a pixelated version of the IO logo and is named eight-bit according to the url. Next I found 10001000, which shows the &ldquo;synth&rdquo; module.</p>

<p>I google a binary-to-text convert and found that these represented some interesting values — the convert return HTML special character codes — nor did they seem particularly relevant. 0101001 yields &ldquo;S&rdquo;, whereas 10001000 yields &ldquo;&#710;&rdquo;, a circumflex (hooray for new words).</p>

<p>Naturally, I had to know more. I creatively googled &ldquo;google io experiment&rdquo; and found the <a href="https://github.com/Instrument/google-io-2013">GitHub page</a>. Yay open source! Using GitHub&rsquo;s search bar, I plugged in the first number set (01010011) and found a list of <a href="https://github.com/Instrument/google-io-2013/blob/fe814b62e68fcd5db481d348a2ae0fdb2a6f6d4a/js/mode.js">all possible combinations</a>. (Conveniently commented in, too, I might add. Else I might&rsquo;ve never found them :3). Some of the inputs appear to not be accepted (notably 10101010, reportedly the &ldquo;metaball&rdquo; mode, and 10010110, the &ldquo;donut&rdquo; mode, and a few look as if they might have minor bugs (mentioned in the comments for the first batch, lines 65-69, plus I noticed some visual effects in Eight Bit), but the rest appear to be in working order. My favorite one is SpaceMode, 00101010.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Cheap Valentine's Day Card Audio Circuit]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/building-a-cheap-valentines-day-card-audio-circuit/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T19:43:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/building-a-cheap-valentines-day-card-audio-circuit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About two weeks before Valetine&rsquo;s Day, I got the idea of making a Zelda-themed card for a friend of mine. She and I are both big Zelda fans. I searched the web for a  card, until I found <a href="(http://blog.close-encounters.com.au/2013/02/normal-0-false-false-false.html">this one</a> that I liked because of the extra dimensions. It seems that the pop-up style heart container card is a pretty popular one overall, and this is one of many.</p>

<p>I decided to take it another step, incoporating some of my (few) electronics skills into the project. To be honest, it was mostly an excuse to order some parts off of Digikey and super-nerdify what would otherwise be a fairly straightforward project. But hey! It was extraordinarily fun.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So did some research for recordable card circuits, and I found <a href="http://hackaday.com/2011/11/22/musical-greeting-card-with-minimal-parts/">this Hackaday post</a> about how to make one on my own. I&rsquo;d been to Digikey&rsquo;s website before, but I had never made an order. Consequently, I had no idea what I was in for. I decided to go through with the project, and ended up ordering all the parts about a week in advance. After a minor issue with shipping a lithium-ion battery through UPS and <em>actually finding everything</em>, I got the parts on the Thursday night before Valentine&rsquo;s Day. I had some debugging left to do, so it was a fairly long night. It was by all means worth it.</p>

<p>The card itself is a relatively simple papercraft model, with some space inside to fit components. I printed it on some cardstock and cut it using an exacto knife.</p>

<h4>About the code</h4>

<p>I had a bit of an educational experience working on the code. I&rsquo;m familiar with Javascript and Python, and I&rsquo;ve worked with Arduino before, but I&rsquo;d never before really wrote new components. I used a modified version of the <a href="http://www.arduino.cc/en/Tutorial/Melody">Arduino&rsquo;s Melody example code</a>. Initially, I tuned the values with a tuning application (Instuner on the App Store) for the piezo buzzer, and added flat/sharp notes, as well as some notes an octave up I&rsquo;d need to play the bit of music. The code, more or less the same but with tuned values, is <a href="https://github.com/ianklatzco/melody_revised">on GitHub</a>. I then manually wrote transcribed the notes from some sheet music of the specific tune into the code, resulting in <a href="https://github.com/ianklatzco/melody_revised/blob/master/zelda_chest_noise.ino">this</a>.</p>

<h4>Hardware and writing the code to the ATtiny</h4>

<p>The electronics components were a bit trickier. I ordered about $5 in parts (<a href="http://i.imgur.com/bJdj4Qz.png">parts list</a>) along with some spare ATtinies for future projects. Initially, I thought that I would use a piezo buzzer and reed switch in the circuit, but in the end I opted for a speaker I had on hand (16ohm, 0.5w, salvaged from a similar, pre-recorded greeting card with a ROM) and a regular (SPST) switch (salvaged from the inside of a vending machine). Here&rsquo;s a photo of the (poorly drawn) circuit diagram:
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/0ULfMSj.jpg" alt="circuit diagram" />
Here&rsquo;re some of the parts:
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/QpoaPIs.jpg" alt="parts" /></p>

<p>I connected pins 0 and 1 on the ATtiny to the speaker and switch, respectively. After soldering everything in place, I decided that the reed switch was too difficult to align, so I swapped it for the SPST. I wrote the final version of the code to the ATtiny (or so I thought), connected the battery, and everything looked like it was good to go.</p>

<p>Suddenly, an eerie croaking noise came out of the speaker, audibly changing tones but doing so very slowly. As it was already about midnight at that, I panicked. I guessed the issue was the clock rate on the chip — I tested the code on the Arduino, which boasts a 20MHz crystal (which actually runs at 16MHz most of the time), as opposed to the ATtiny, which has a paltry 1MHz. A quick google search found a <a href="http://electronics.stackexchange.com/questions/7859/how-do-i-set-the-clock-speed-fuses-on-an-attiny85-when-using-an-arduino-as-a-pro">Stack Exchange</a> post that told me that I should multiply all values by a factor of sixteen, which worked splendidly. The notes were out of tune, and the croaking sounds remained, but it wasn&rsquo;t nearly as bad as before. The final code is also <a href="https://github.com/ianklatzco/melody_revised/blob/master/zelda_chest_noise_x16.ino">on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h4>Using the Arduino as an ISP (to program the ATtiny)</h4>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/mtKQXWc.jpg" alt="programming" />
In order to program the ATtiny, I used the Arduino. I followed the guide at <a href="http://highlowtech.org/?p=1695">highlowtech.org</a> and it worked, if not with a few hiccups. Initially, I was pushing the ATtiny and a socket down into the breadboard, before I realized that the ATTiny could be pushed directly into it.</p>

<h4>Final Product</h4>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/ansXraLD05M" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>


<p>I have to thank two friends of mine, who provided awesome help throughout this project. Both who work in the tech industry. If you&rsquo;re a high school student, you should definitely try to communicate with professionals who work in positions you&rsquo;d like to have. If you&rsquo;re a professional, you should be open to helping kids pursue their interests. The relationships I&rsquo;ve developed have been extremely beneficial.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Hilarious Side Note</h4>

<p>Listening to serial communication is the coolest thing ever. It sounds a bit like a dial-up modem.</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/nlxuCgJxEsg" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessing the Admin Panel on Coke Freestyle Machines]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/accessing-the-admin-panel-on-coke-freestyle-machines/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-31T22:23:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/accessing-the-admin-panel-on-coke-freestyle-machines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, a Meatheads burger joint opened up just down the street from my house. As a method of celebrating my first driver&rsquo;s license and to say fareweall to the pair of Lithuanians that had stayed with us through the week, we decided to go get some lunch.</p>

<p>While there, I noticed a pair of those snazzy new Coke machines, the kind that let you pick a multitude of flavors and mix it with various popular beverages. My brother reminded me that we had found the admin panel on a previous visit, so we decided to look for it again.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/auJEpJe.jpg" alt="coke machine pic" /></p>

<p>The dispenser appears to have some sort of touch screen (resistive? capacitive?) that&rsquo;s something of a pain to actually use.</p>

<p>Acessing the admin panel is pretty straightforward. All you have to do is select the water icon/bubble, place five fingers around it on the screen, and then mash it until a loading box appears. From that screen you can see the current levels of the various syrups that make up the myriad drinks available.</p>

<p>You can&rsquo;t really do much with the screen, since the actual access panels (Admin, Technician, Supplier I believe) are locked with a password. But it&rsquo;s certainly fun doing some harmless sneaking about.</p>

<hr />

<p>Here&rsquo;s a video of it being done.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/PlUpkZjw3vA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why 1:1 iPad Programs Suck.]]></title>
    <link href="http://klatz.co/blog/why-1-1-ipad-programs-suck/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T17:43:02-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://klatz.co/blog/why-1-1-ipad-programs-suck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I consider myself a pretty efficient worker when I get down to it. Not that I work all the time (actually, I don&rsquo;t work much of the time, but that&rsquo;s another issue), but that I work with optimal utilization of available resources (read: I like configuring my gadgets to help me do things). It comes from a childhood of ample freedom with tech, in that my father always let me to take things from him and put them into the most useful form. Beyond that, I like technology. Hell, I love technology, and the productivity boosts it offers. So you might imagine my elation when my school announced it would begin a 1:1 iPad program starting this year.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Bias against Apple aside, I had always entertained the notion of walking into my classes with a computing device. The particular draw was the ability to record homework assignments into <a href="http://www.wunderlist.com">Wunderlist</a> (which, as you can see below, has grown of of control pretty quickly). I dreamed of a day where I could freely check my email, google an unknown topic, or zero my RSS feeds on the fly—and that day came.</p>

<p>But it came with more inconveniences than I could have ever imagined. There are two major problems.</p>

<ul>
<li>Books <strong>must</strong> be on iPads. (Apparently the administration that approved the program never knew this would be a requirement.)</li>
<li>The tech policy is incredibly vague.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/6bFnaKI.jpg" alt="silliness" /></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s my iPad for composition. One monitor has a screenshot of my ipad for the assignment. Another my todo list and the book page itself, the pages also screenshots.</p>

<p>I fail to see how this is more efficient than a book and a notebook and an assignment book. The amount of underlying infrastructure that I have setup to get everything running is utterly ridiculous. Granted, I love typing instead of writing, but the point stands. Notability, Dropbox>Camera Uploads, iOS running on two devices that need to be plugged in at the same time, all of this is absurd. I consider myself technologically-inclined. But I&rsquo;m overwhelmed at the amount of setup I need to compensate for the complexities of the iPad program. I can hardly imagine the struggles it causes for people who aren&rsquo;t technologically inclined. After one teacher mentioned that he had heard of one student whose parents bought him two iPads (one for the book, another for note taking), I seriously considered it.</p>

<p>Admittedly, I am inclined to overcomplicating things, and I tend to be a bit spoiled technology-wise, and I very well might be overcomplicating this. But I think it&rsquo;d be pretty difficult to simplify the setup to not use two screens. Switching between Notability and the textbook is a pain.</p>

<p>I would be perfectly content with a book, or digital book applications that didn&rsquo;t suck. The vast majority of them are buggy or full of DRM.</p>

<p>Now, iPads are extraordinarily convenient in that they&rsquo;re light. I&rsquo;ve opted for an extraordinarily light backpack, instead of my usually excessively hefty one. I never go to my locker anymore. I rarely forget books, since the majority of them are on my iPad. On the other hand, however, when the internet goes down, I lose half of my books. Because DRM sucks.</p>

<p>I appreciate my relatively conservative school&rsquo;s attempts to remain at the forefront of tech adoption. But trying to depend on a system that&rsquo;s not really there doesn&rsquo;t really work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
